hey what's up guys my name is the chana
welcome back to my estate plus plus
series so last time we talked about how
you can actually use libraries in C++
and your C++ project and specifically
how you can link them statically but
today we're talking all about dynamic
linking what it is how to use it when
you should be using it more that stuff
and this time we're going to be linking
JFW dynamically so in the static video
we linked it statically and now we're
gonna link it dynamically and kind of
see what what was involved in that and
what the differences are so first of all
dynamic linking what what does it mean
how is it different than static why is
it called dynamic so dynamic linking is
linking that happens at runtime so
static linking happens at compile time
when you compile a static library you
then link it into either an executable
an application or a dynamic library and
that's kind of it you're done you
literally take the contents of that
static library and you put it into black
with the rest of the binary data that's
actually in your dynamic library or
inside your executable and because of
that there are there are a number of
optimizations that can happen because
the compiler and linker is now fully
aware of the code that actually goes
into an application when you're linked
statically when we talk more about the
actual performance differences in what
Ward linking statically versus
dynamically actually means in a future
video this is just a basic overview but
just keep that in mind that static
linking kind of allows more of that
optimization to happen because the
compiler and linker kind of is just they
can see more of the picture specifically
the link that can see more of the more
of the picture whereas dynamic linking
as I mentioned happens at runtime what
that means is that when you actually
launch your executable that is when your
dynamic link library gets loaded so it's
not actually part of the executable when
you launch normal executable it gets
loaded into memory however if you have a
dynamic link library what that means is
that you actually link another library
and external binary file dynamically at
runtime so you run your application and
then you load an additional file into
memory now the way that executables work
they can actually require certain
libraries to be present certain dynamic
libraries certain external files to be
present before they actually let you run
the application
that's why on Windows for example you
might sometimes see when you launch an
application you might sometimes see our
message pop up being like blah blah or
DLL is required or is not found
so we can start the program and that's
one form of dynamic linking that's kind
of I like to almost call that kind of
50/50 because they're executable is
aware of the dynamic link library and it
actually lists it as a requirement but
it is still a separate file a separate
module that is loaded at runtime you can
also load dynamic link libraries
completely like dynamically so the
executable can have nothing to do with
it at all you can launch your executable
your application it won't even ask you
to include a certain dynamic library but
then inside your executable you can
actually write code which looks for and
maybe loads certain dynamic libraries at
one time and that obtains function
pointers or whatever you need to the
stuff that's inside that dynamic library
and then uses that dynamic library so we
don't have libraries just keep that in
mind that's kind of the static dynamic
version which is basically my
application actually requires that this
dynamic like link library be present and
I'm already up I'm already aware of what
functions are in it and what I can use
but then there's also I want to
arbitrarily load this dynamic library I
don't know what I don't even know what's
in it but I want to pull out some stuff
or I want to do many things with it and
there are very good uses for both of
them we're gonna well we're actually
gonna focus on the formal one for today
which is I know my application requires
this library but I'm going to link it
dynamically set of statically so let's
just jump into an example and look at
what that looks like for GL of W because
gel W actually lets us link either
statically or dynamically so a lot so in
that static so in that static linking
video we basically just linked our jail
it'll be statically we included the
header file and we call gob in it if I
run my program you'll see that it
compiled successfully and it prints one
as our result here now not everything is
going to change if you link dynamically
this include for example remains
identical I mean the header file
supports both static and dynamic linking
there are actually differences that need
to occur with your declarations for
things like functions if you want to
link statically versus dynamically and
we'll explore that in a minute but G
love W like most libraries actually kind
of supports both static and dynamic
linking with that same header file as
we'll see in a minute so this doesn't
change and if I right click on my
project you go to properties you'll see
that under CC busbars general I have
that include part again if you know 100%
sure about how to set all of this
definitely watch my last video on static
blinking even if you're only ever
interested in dynamic linking you still
need to know what static linking is
because a lot of times you'll actually
probably want to link statically if you
can instead of dynamically so check that
out if you're not sure this doesn't
change and then if we go into linker
input we see that we have GL fw3 Lib so
if I open up my folder with GL w now
just right-click here get open folder
and file explorer and then over here in
my file explorer I'm just going to go
back here into dependencies jail of W
and Lib so you can see here that I've
got three files jail also p3 don't live
which is clearly the one that we're
actually currently linking the static
library let's go ahead and get rid of
this one and replaced it with the
dynamic version if we go back over here
you can see clearly that we have to kind
of dll files well one one of those
actually called jail that we three dll
Lib that one is just basically a series
of pointers into kind of this dll file
so that we don't have to actually
retrieve the locations of everything at
runtime it's very important that these
two are compiled at the same time
because if you try and kind of use a
different static library to link with a
dll at one time you're probably going to
get functions mismatching and wrong kind
of memory addresses for function
pointers and just it's not gonna work
out basically what I'm saying so this of
course is distributed by jail fw so they
were compiled at the same time and they
are related directly to each other that
you can't separate these two so back
over here I'm going to type in jail of
w3 DLL lib and that's all we have to do
from this side now if I hit OK and I try
and build this it's going to work
successfully right so you can see that
it's generated my executable file
fighters remove this over here I don't
really cares about the errorless anyway
output is where it's at
I'll move this over here you can see
that HelloWorld exe has successfully
been generated let's try and launch our
application now all right and you can
see that we get this error message that
I talked about earlier the code
execution cannot proceed because Java
b3o tol was not found this is where we
actually have to show our program this
is Jill Toby thread of DLL
right I've got it over here please Lord
and the way that we do that in a simple
case is just basically placing that dll
file in the same location
as out executable so if I got makea I
can copy this dll file go back over here
interdependencies HelloWorld debug and
you can say this is the path with my
executable if I paste this in here and I
go back to either visual studio I could
run it from there as well and I try and
run my program you can see that it works
successfully and we actually get one
over here all right beautiful if I go
back over here to my actual Windows
Explorer I can also double click on
polar world and you can see that it runs
just fine in here without bedroom studio
without any kind of debug is attached as
well so that's all there is to it we
link against the static library and then
we actually make sure that we have the
DLL in and in an accessible place you
can throw out your application actually
set paths to certain libraries like
search locations but the root folder of
your executable so the folder that
actually contains your application is
just automatically kind of a search path
so if you put it into the same folder if
you put your DLL file into the same
folder as your executable you'll be fine
okay so one more thing that I wanted to
mention is if we take a look at this
actual header file we can kind of start
to see the differences between what
happens during static and dynamic
linking specifically if we look at
pretty much any function over here
you'll see that it defines geo wapi
before the return type and then the
actual function name so if I go to the
definition of that and there's a few
definitions lost click on the first one
you can see we have this whole thing
here we've got this case for each we're
on Windows and we're trying to build the
DLL file then it has to actually export
the DLL functions this is actually
really important if you build it without
this it's not gonna work then there's
also win32 and just gelato BDL which
means we're calling here shall be as a
win32 dll which does deathless bacterial
input and then finally there's also the
building the static library and then
calling a GL of dopiaza static library
which is to find the show w api is
nothing so that's actually what's being
defined right now now here's an
interesting question
we are still defining Jeff w API as
nothing even though we're using it as an
actual DLL so shouldn't GLW dll be
defined if we go back to the main if I
go to properties over here and I go into
my c c++ preprocessor and then I add
that progresses the definition gfw dll
is try and compile the code one more
time okay seems pretty legit here it is
let's hit f5 and it runs and it looks
like it runs in exactly the same way so
what's going on here why did I not have
to define deco spec DLL input why did I
have to just like even nothing works and
why is that and that is a question for
you guys you've been asking me for a
while to give you kind of challenges and
things to do for homework or whatever is
a great example why is this happening
why am I able why do I not have to
actually death respect the other import
to be able to link to these functions in
my DLL file successfully leave a comment
below whoever wins this will just get
pinned as the comment that's you guys a
pretty decent prize I'm alright but yeah
just leave leave a comment below and
we'll see who can figure it out anyway
thanks for watching I hope you guys
enjoy this video if you did you can hit
that like button any more questions
about dynamic linking about static
linking all that stuff leave a comment
below as well as hop on my discord that
which is the channel to come such
discord there's a bunch of people there
talking about pretty much everything to
do with C++ and OpenGL and graphics and
programming and just everything it's a
really good time if you really like this
video and you want to help support the
series that I do here on YouTube then
you can go to patreon.com/scishow Cherno
so guess the pretty cool rewards like
getting videos early and lots of other
fun stuff so definitely check that out
and I'll see you guys next time good bye
[Music]